move into move towards the models of
cognitive development that look more
closely at meaning-making versus
cognitive capacity and the first person
we want to look at is the work of
Michael bus stations and he's done a lot
of work directly with looking at
dialectical systems and dialectical
reasoning in cognitive development and
he actually claims that the that dialect
there's a dialectical stage of cognitive
development and of course the skill sets
people discount this because they're
they claim it's only a phase in formal
operations but facetious likes to
highlight how much different on the move
or the movement or the growth toward
dialectical reasoning is then formal
operational reasoning and so he makes a
claim that it should be as discreet lyst
age or a level jump up from formal
operations so there's to look at work
from the general to the more specific
there's two phases that announce the
full-blown dialectical stage of
cognitive development in this type of
research in the first phase is this is
pre dialectical is just ordinary dualism
and in the ordinary dualism phase we see
that people are reasoning from one or
the other category in a dualistic pair
so that people might bias
their judgment on a subjective
perspective whereas other people might
bias their perspective on an objective
perspective now for the most part most
people dance back and forth depending
upon what problem they're looking at and
so dualism means that do that people are
are biased in one of the other but they
can dance back and forth without knowing
so that there isn't there's there's
there's unconscious bias but that both
sides of the argument or both roles are
available to people so within you go you
might go to a science class and kind of
understand that there's an objective
perspective required and then you could
go to English class and you have a
subjective perspective so the people can
dance back and forth but in each
individual case of what what their role
is or what their domain is they're
taking one half one side of the
dualistic perspective so the the next
phase is a very subtle phases is that
people begin to see this dance this
dance becomes apparent to them and their
reasoning becomes more relativistic so
they start to qualify their arguments
arguments
they start to qualify their judgments
okay they start to include context so we
might say well reasoning from this
perspective I would have answer a
reasoning from that perspective I would
nuance be then I would want to add a
little taste of the perspective of scene
so you get this more complex but perhaps
less firm orientation toward the answer
of the truth and so this is the
relativistic stage which is aware of
this dance and tries to contextualize
the multiple perspectives and this is
what then becomes the dialectical mind
because this dance is not very
satisfactory relativism is not
satisfactory and so so the move toward
dialectical thinking which is a movement
a effective movement let's say movement
toward a greater understanding is what
is sought so there's in the Oh broad
scheme of it people are initially
dualistic in their reasoning although
they can dance between different
dualistic poles then they become aware
of this dance and there
tends to be relativistic and then the
pressures for problem solving or
resolving the ambiguity in the
relativistic stage creates what
facetious would call dialectical mind or
dialectical reasoning so there's a real
this in its this level that he would
argue is a discrete stage beyond formal
operational facetious has labeled or
categorized two types of dialectical
reasoning and he categorizes that as
dialectical so beyond the dualistic and
relativistic stages and then he
categorizes late stage dialectical and
so we can look at those in a grid form
here I'm not a very successful line but
there we go and so in dialectical stage
we see the person is reasoning through
logical categories that there's a clear
on reasoning profit process through
thesis antithesis and synthesis that if
you diagram their arguments this is very
clearly their progression that the
systems or the organization of reality
that they end up with tend to be
composite structures
or we could say that the approach is
constructivist so they build up
information so this concept of building
up for building on ideas in a
dialectical way the end product is
synthetic not surprising because this
move towards our synthesis or we might
say it's algorithmic that makes it still
linear so that everything that was
included in the premises is built up to
a synthetic form that completely
includes all the pieces so like nested
sets or transcend and include so they
end up with a transcendent hole which
gives them the impression that knowledge
itself is a transcendent the game thing
and that they operate primarily through
the lens of theory and their
understanding is that reality is
perspectival but that there is the
ability to get a universal perspective
perspective on a problem through this
process if you if you work this process
long enough or hard enough or accurately
enough yes that's a perspective but it's
a universal perspective and pastiches
says something different happens in
late-stage dial
ethical and the reason why don't what
happens is that people begin to be able
to see this process right so they can
see this process happening in and start
to undermine the constructivist approach
because they can see that it's dependent
upon these conditions which are
processes of the cognitive mind and so
they move toward a different view of
meaning and move through or work through
some of the limitations of the
dialectical stage so that because they
become aware of this movement of mind
through thesis antithesis and fit system
synthesis they start to to organize the
world in terms of forms of existence so
for example you will they start to
organize the world in terms of
perspectives those perspectives are now
a form of existence or whole lines which
are not processes of the mind but forms
of existence or quadrivium you'll hear
that term these are all forms of
existence instead of composite
structures they have what we might call
constitutive structures so these are all
members not parts and instead of being
constructivist we see that they're
looking at the dynamics Amara's
emergence so constituted parts are
members not constructed or composite
parts
instead of synthetic move we have an
integrated move that is more relational
so if you have members not parts then
the parts don't get completely included
like a nested set their relationally
members in a more integrated fashion so
this is the way the late-stage
dialectical mind is operating instead
have a transcendent whole there is the
sense of a prior hole or the ground of
being of these prior whole the ground of
these forms of existence that is trying
to be in a sense recapitulated instead
of transcendent knowledge you have
collective knowledge from all these
numbers instead of theory the
operational form is meta theoretical and
instead of perspective a universal
perspective it's multi perspectival you
can see some of this bomb is similar to
some of the evolutionary changes that we
see that we talked about before so this
is Bush the fishes is schematic just to
give you a little preview we can
contrast this to what I would call the
transition to the next movement which
are calling on to logic to see just how
crisp
can be made between dialectical and
ontological and just to see what you
think so instead of logical categories
or forms of existence we have
ontological categories which are
temporal tones like anterior and
posterior so this is the first time that
time itself is incorporated as a
category and contextualized it's still
and also now instead of constructivist
or constitute constitutive structures we
have ontogenetic relations in generative
processes instead of synthetic or
integrity dynamics we have generative
processes or process dynamics instead of
transcendent holes of the idea of a
prior whole we have mutually generative
holes and parts and then emphasis here
is on generative the dynamics between
the holes in part instead of the notion
of the transcendent knowledge or the
goal of collective knowledge we have a
recognition of implicit knowing that the
knower is implicit in the process it's
itself
whereas in dialectical reasoning the
methodology of argument is theoretical
in late-stage dialectical its emphasis
is on neta theory of the move toward
meta theory and the ontological mind
these are considered to be creative
imaginaries and so you have this
profound shift between the situation in
both of these where theory is a tool to
get at reality and that the theory
somehow is reality to this move that
creative imagination it imaginaries that
you use your creative imagination to
bring up certain aspects of reality that
may be more relevant meaningful or
useful but there is this notion this
complete transparency that we are always
creating theories in imaginary ways as a
tool to make inquiry and the
justification for that is that we are
situated in being and we have this
implicit knowing and so there's this
phrase I like to use is that whereas
before the theories have us as if they
are somehow more real than just our
imaginations afterwards we are
completely aware that we are using our
mind in a creative way as a instrument
of inquiry and in these final categories
here whereas originally there's this
concept of a universal perspective
illness versus a multi or hierarchical
perspectival then in the ontological
mind the basic structure of the cosmos
is seen as being a perspectival or open
or what gabster likes to say is
diaphanous
and so I just set this out that before
we go on to the next section of this
video so you might be able to see some
of these aspects as being important in
what the meaning based developmental
cognitive models see as some of the
highest stages of adult cognitive
capacity so just be aware and look for
some of the indications of these aspects
of what I'm calling an ontological art
of this video we